<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Stuff | Design Disclosure - Portfolio & Personal Blog of Alistair Stead]]></title>
  <link href="http://alistairstead.github.com/blog/categories/stuff/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alistairstead.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-19T22:21:38+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://alistairstead.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alistair Stead]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[alistair.stead@designdisclosure.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updated Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://alistairstead.github.com/2012/02/updated-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-13T17:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://alistairstead.github.com/2012/02/updated-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It has been an absolute age since I last created any new content for this blog. The main reason has been simply that I have been very very busy doing other things. However it is also that due to the fact that creating content through a browser and storing it in a database just did not fit with the way I work.</p>

<p>I spend most of my day working in a terminal window. I choose a text editor over an IDE, speed and flexibility over features. Okay I don't go all the way back to basics I use <a href="http://blog.macromates.com/2011/textmate-2-0-alpha/">TextMate</a> and <a href="http://www.iterm2.com/">iTerm</a> with <a href="http://www.zsh.org/">ZSH</a> and <a href="https://github.com/robbyrussell/oh-my-zsh">oh-my-zsh</a>. All of these things let me work in the simplest most flexible way.</p>

<p>My blog on the other hand always felt restrictive. So after some conversation on twitter /cc @mpmlopes @__debo I spent a couple of hours over the weekend making the leap to <a href="http://octopress.org/">octopress</a>. Although not loaded with features this lets me create content in the simplest format, markdown in this case and using Git and some Ruby it is baked into a static blog hosted on <a href="http://github.com/">Github</a> using Github pages.</p>

<p>As you can see this has allowed me to create new content. Okay it is just an 'Updated Blog' statement but it is a statement of more to come. Some of what has been keeping me busy for the last 12 months should be good enough to create new posts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
